<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en_US"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://www.jrdnbwmn.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://www.jrdnbwmn.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en_US" /><updated>2019-01-16T13:13:34-07:00</updated><id>https://www.jrdnbwmn.com/</id><title type="html">Jordan Bowman</title><subtitle>I make stuff for the web and interview entrepreneurs.</subtitle><author><name>jrdnbwmn</name></author><entry><title type="html">William Candillon on transparency, target markets, and developers building businesses</title><link href="https://www.jrdnbwmn.com/post/william-candillon-on-transparency-target-markets-and-developers-building-businesses/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="William Candillon on transparency, target markets, and developers building businesses" /><published>2018-04-24T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2018-04-24T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>https://www.jrdnbwmn.com/post/william-candillon-on-transparency-target%20markets-and-developers-building-businesses</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.jrdnbwmn.com/post/william-candillon-on-transparency-target-markets-and-developers-building-businesses/">&lt;p&gt;William Candillon is a 31-year-old software engineer from France. He built &lt;a href=&quot;https://react-native.shop/&quot;&gt;React Native Starter Kits&lt;/a&gt; during a sabbatical and now has &lt;a href=&quot;http://github.com/wcandillon&quot;&gt;repos&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/@wcandillon&quot;&gt;writing&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/channel/UC806fwFWpiLQV5y-qifzHnA&quot;&gt;videos&lt;/a&gt; centered on React Native development. William currently lives in beautiful Zürich, Switzerland.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;youre-big-into-transparency-what-are-the-benefits-of-being-transparent&quot;&gt;You’re big into transparency. What are the benefits of being transparent?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the case of the React Native Starter Kits, transparency as helped on two fronts. It enabled me to validate the product/market fit before investing a lot of work into the product. And once the product was ready, transparency has helped customers to get better insights about what they are buying, as well as better support.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From the get-go I shared my plans with the community. I built a landing page that contained screenshots of the finished product, even though not a single line of code was written yet. People could leave their email if they were interested in getting the kit once it was ready. This landing page was linked into my medium stories on React Native.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After that, when the product picked up momentum, I started to code the starter kits live on YouTube. Not only has it been an enjoyable process, but the feedback from the community has been great, and it really gives potential customers a sense of what they would be buying. It has also helped tremendously with customer support. Many questions can be answered by pointing to the right YouTube video.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;how-did-you-figure-out-who-your-target-market-is&quot;&gt;How did you figure out who your target market is?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A market place for React Native app already existed: &lt;a href=&quot;https://market.nativebase.io/&quot;&gt;NativeBase Market Place&lt;/a&gt;. This was extremely convenient because it takes time to build your own sales channel. Today, half of the sales are made directly, but it took many months to get to that result. So having an existing marketplace for the product was very valuable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The size of the React Native community is substantial, but there is a lot of mistrust in these starter kits, as there should be! 😅 Beginners in the community might not have enough knowledge to grasp the value provided by these kits, and people who are advanced enough to understand the value might consider doing it themselves, just because it’s fun to do. Therefore, the targeted segment in this large community is relatively small.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;what-are-the-unique-challenges-and-advantages-youve-experienced-as-a-developer-who-is-trying-to-build-a-business&quot;&gt;What are the unique challenges and advantages you’ve experienced as a developer who is trying to build a business?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a developer, I’m focused on code quality, trying to reduce technical debt as much as possible, and delivering the best product possible. The downside of this love for good software engineering is that other aspects of the product like online marketing get neglected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Developers always want to build cool things and continuously improve on them. But with the React Native Starter Kits, it is now clear to me that sometimes commercial data should drive the process instead.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>jrdnbwmn</name></author><category term="transparency" /><category term="target market" /><category term="query" /><summary type="html">William Candillon is a 31-year-old software engineer from France. He built React Native Starter Kits during a sabbatical and now has repos, writing, and videos centered on React Native development. William currently lives in beautiful Zürich, Switzerland.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Arif Tukiman on niches, international audiences, and customers vs competitors</title><link href="https://www.jrdnbwmn.com/post/arif-tukiman-on-niches-international-audiences-and-customers-vs-competitors/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Arif Tukiman on niches, international audiences, and customers vs competitors" /><published>2018-04-18T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2018-04-18T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>https://www.jrdnbwmn.com/post/arif-tukiman-on-niches-international-audiences-and-customers-vs-competitors</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.jrdnbwmn.com/post/arif-tukiman-on-niches-international-audiences-and-customers-vs-competitors/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/arifcooll&quot;&gt;Arif Tukiman&lt;/a&gt; is CEO of Cool Code and back in January 2017, their team released &lt;a href=&quot;https://runcloud.io/&quot;&gt;RunCloud&lt;/a&gt;, which is a cloud server panel. It helps you set up, configure, manage, and monitor your VPSes on cloud hosting providers, and is specifically for PHP applications. Arif lives in Johor Bahru, Malaysia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;why-did-you-decide-to-drill-down-on-a-really-specific-niche-for-runcloud-and-what-have-been-the-benefits-of-doing-that&quot;&gt;Why did you decide to drill down on a really specific niche for RunCloud and what have been the benefits of doing that?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We built RunCloud to help our own web developers and the issues they faced during development, deployment, and maintenance. Based on their response, we saw the potential to productize the software — we just knew it could help other developers dealing with the same problems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The story really begins two years ago. My partner, Fikri, took the idea and thought that perhaps we could develop a tool for web hosting providers, but we didn’t have a ready and stable product at the time. We soon realized that the market was very competitive in that area with the presence of established players like WHM, CPanel, and Plesk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So in early 2016, we pivoted our solution to cater more narrowly to PHP developers and freelance web designers. It’s a market closer to our hearts, given that we ourselves are PHP developers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We validated the idea for this narrower product by taking a look at the market and checking out competitors. There were indeed competitors, but no major players like CPanel or Plesk. The businesses in our space were also just about 2-3 years in age at the time. And checking out their features, we believed we could offer the market something better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My partners and I are computer science graduates. Amir and I were more into mobile app development. My other partner, Fikri, has more experience in security and web. Previously, Fikri had also created a VPN service that he’d sold subscriptions for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To build RunCloud as a business, I had to take on the role of CEO. Amir assumed the role of COO and led our marketing efforts, while Fikri, the brains behind the RunCloud architecture, became the CTO.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we started working on the product, we were just college kids fresh out of our master’s degree. We had no work experience. So to be honest, money-wise, there was not a lot to spare.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fortunately, we were also single college kids who didn’t require much to survive on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;what-are-the-challenges-associated-with-targeting-an-international-market-how-have-you-dealt-with-those-challenges&quot;&gt;What are the challenges associated with targeting an international market? How have you dealt with those challenges?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We started charging from day one. We knew we had a good product by comparing ourselves to competitors who were charging way more for less features. Our packages are simple. A free account and a $10 per month account for an unlimited number of servers. That was the only way we knew we could make money then. (Of course, things have since changed.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We use Braintree to charge our customers. This is the easiest solution for us, a Malaysian company, to be able to charge customers that come from all over the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So far, we’ve reached about 5,700 users from more than 25 countries worldwide. From current conversion to paid user, our MRR has been steadily growing at 24-29% from month to month.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think this is in line with a lesson we learned from legendary Jay Abraham when it comes to growing revenue. There are generally only three ways to go about it:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;More customers&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Bigger purchases per customer&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;More frequent purchases (from customers who come back)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a SaaS business, we’re already doing #3. And we are always working to acquire more customers, so that covers #1. And now, at last, we have #2.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the Backup Service, we are adding something else that customers can pay us for. To be honest, this wasn’t the original intention. We’d received a lot of feedback asking for a backup feature, so we implemented it. While we did have other plans and priorities a few months ago, we decided to listen to our customers’ needs instead. And I think that has already paid off very well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Along those lines is a gem from &lt;a href=&quot;https://thefoundation.com/&quot;&gt;Dane Maxwell&lt;/a&gt; that I’d like to share: “In business, you will make a lot of mistakes and you will do alright if you do this one thing right — listen to your customers.” Great advice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Honestly, when it comes to our own survival, RunCloud does not provide enough to cover our own wages yet. We still take in custom mobile and web application work. At times, we provide training related to programming. What we earn from RunCloud will most probably go back into the business. Earning in USD while living in Malaysia does help with living expenses, as they are low compared to USA or Europe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;whats-the-balance-between-building-for-customers-vs-competitors&quot;&gt;What’s the balance between building for customers vs competitors?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pay constant attention to your customers; don’t become so preoccupied with the activities of your competitors that you forget about your own business. Focus on improving your own business and ensuring that everyone who is associated with it has a great customer experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think Jeff Bezos said it best: “Obsess about customers, not competitors.”&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>jrdnbwmn</name></author><category term="niches" /><category term="customers" /><category term="competition" /><category term="query" /><summary type="html">Arif Tukiman is CEO of Cool Code and back in January 2017, their team released RunCloud, which is a cloud server panel. It helps you set up, configure, manage, and monitor your VPSes on cloud hosting providers, and is specifically for PHP applications. Arif lives in Johor Bahru, Malaysia.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Manuel Frigerio on pricing, paid advertising, and Product Hunt</title><link href="https://www.jrdnbwmn.com/post/manuel-frigerio-on-pricing-paid-advertising-and-product-hunt/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Manuel Frigerio on pricing, paid advertising, and Product Hunt" /><published>2018-04-10T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2018-04-10T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>https://www.jrdnbwmn.com/post/manuel-frigerio-on-pricing-paid-advertising-and-product-hunt</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.jrdnbwmn.com/post/manuel-frigerio-on-pricing-paid-advertising-and-product-hunt/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://manuel.friger.io/&quot;&gt;Manuel Frigerio&lt;/a&gt; is the founder of &lt;a href=&quot;https://maitreapp.co/&quot;&gt;Maître&lt;/a&gt;, which offers multiple tools for viral referral marketing. He is Italian, and lived in London for four years before doing the “digital nomad thing”™ for 8 months in south-east Asia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;what-have-been-your-pricing-decisions-for-maître-and-how-has-that-affected-the-overall-success-of-the-product&quot;&gt;What have been your pricing decisions for Maître and how has that affected the overall success of the product?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve changed my mind about pricing 100 times. In the beginning, I went for a one-off fee simply because I couldn’t be bothered building a subscription system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Financially, it was a big mistake. People were getting far more value out of the product than what I was charging for. In short, I was leaving money on the table. Being priced so low had the obvious advantage of being very attractive for startups, which helped in the early days, but ultimately we didn’t want to be the cheapest on the market but the best.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since then, we have increased the pricing 5 times and moved to a subscription model. That move has meant first of all the financial survival of the company and expanding the team to support our ever-growing number of customers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;what-are-your-thoughts-on-paid-advertising-for-early-startups&quot;&gt;What are your thoughts on paid advertising for early startups?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just avoid it. It’s simply not worth the hassle. Like many startups, we tried paid ads and like almost everyone we gave up after wasting a few hundred dollars.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The problem with paid ads for early startups is that very few people actually know how to set up a decent campaign. And without that knowledge, you’re very likely to waste money.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And regardless of your knowledge, early startups should focus on recruiting users one-by-one, do “things that don’t scale”. Paid ads might be a strategy that works once you reach product/market fit and you need to scale but in the early days is, at most, laziness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;maître-is-one-of-the-most-upvoted-products-on-product-hunt-can-you-give-us-a-piece-of-advice-for-launching-on-ph-and-tell-us-how-much-of-the-success-there-depends-on-luck&quot;&gt;Maître is one of the most-upvoted products on Product Hunt. Can you give us a piece of advice for launching on PH, and tell us how much of the success there depends on luck?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Product Hunt has changed a lot since we launch on it. Ryan and the PH team have executed incredibly well. That said, I think there is timeless advice when launching on PH.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, be nice. No seriously. Product Hunt is a community, but some people use it as a disposable piece of software. Don’t be that person.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Remember that Product Hunt is not the right place to launch anything. It’s undeniable that the PH community loves some things (crypto, kittens, the 3,285,434th colour palette app) more than others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Preparation is important. Don’t just on PH, plan it carefully. It’s incredible the difference it will make. I’ve actually written a &lt;a href=&quot;https://manuel.friger.io/blog/product-hunt&quot;&gt;blog post&lt;/a&gt; about our launch. Some information is out of date, but most of it is still relevant.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>jrdnbwmn</name></author><category term="pricing" /><category term="paid advertising" /><category term="query" /><summary type="html">Manuel Frigerio is the founder of Maître, which offers multiple tools for viral referral marketing. He is Italian, and lived in London for four years before doing the “digital nomad thing”™ for 8 months in south-east Asia.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Do Aesthetics Matter?</title><link href="https://www.jrdnbwmn.com/post/do-aesthetics-matter/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Do Aesthetics Matter?" /><published>2018-02-27T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2018-02-27T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://www.jrdnbwmn.com/post/do-aesthetics-matter</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.jrdnbwmn.com/post/do-aesthetics-matter/">&lt;p&gt;As a product designer, sometimes I question how important beauty is when it comes to software.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Look at this list of some of the most popular websites on the Internet:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Craigslist&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Reddit&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Hacker News&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Wikipedia&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Drudge Report&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These sites have little to no aesthetic appeal, but collectively they are visited by tens of millions people every day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I ask myself…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Are we just showing off our design skills to other designers? Does the average consumer notice? Do aesthetics have a direct impact on revenue?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are questions worth answering.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;no-aesthetics-dont-matter&quot;&gt;“No, Aesthetics Don’t Matter!”&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some would point to the above examples (and more) to make the case that beauty is irrelevant. They’d say visual design is mostly un-measurable mushy marketing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After all, software is a tool. We use it to accomplish tasks like communicating, writing, checking off a to-do, or socializing with a friend.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Giving the user the ability to perform a unique task is far more important than making it look good.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We jump on Wikipedia because it’s easy to get free encyclopedic information. We pull up Craigslist because we want to buy or sell something locally without having to pay for it. We visit Reddit for its distinctive take.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It doesn’t matter that these sites are ugly because they’re the best tools for their specific job.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, part of the popularity of these sites has become their ugliness. It’s as if the user base is saying, “We just laugh at how ugly Reddit/Drudge Report/Hacker News is because we get quite a lot of utility from it, and that’s what matters most.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can’t build a valueless product, throw some eye-appeal on it, and expect it to last.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Take a rain poncho. This is an incredibly ugly piece of clothing. But millions of them are sold every year because they’re really good at their job — keeping you dry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;yes-aesthetics-do-matter&quot;&gt;“Yes, Aesthetics Do Matter!”&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Others say beauty is critically important.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/1200/1*WdoGi5bDzqndB3pRGsKkrQ.png&quot; alt=&quot;stripe.com&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For companies trying to build or sustain a brand, visual design matters because it’s part of the package. People recognize Stripe, for example, in part because of their stand-out aesthetics. Paul Rand said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Design is the silent ambassador of your brand.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Something beautiful is also pleasing to use. And pleased customers keep coming back. It’s a piece (however small) of user experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When something is beautiful, you can feel that there was some thought put into its creation. That makes it feel professional and gives it an air of having been built on purpose — a feeling that whoever created this thought about you, the user, as they made it. When the opposite is true, it feels like someone just hacked it together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those sites mentioned above — Craigslist, Reddit, etc. — those are the exception. They’re popular in spite of being ugly because they were first to market and have an entrenched user base. For those of us building something new, there’s no reason to purposefully forgo aesthetics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Think back a decade ago to when the very first iPhone came out. The usability and utility were there in abundance, to be sure. But people were also astounded by how beautiful it was. No other phone looked like that. Many people were (and still are) willing to pay an astronomical price for it, in large part because of that beauty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;my-takeaways&quot;&gt;My Takeaways&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Which side are you on?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t think it’s black and white. It’s a matter of priorities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Form follows function.” Function certainly comes first, but that doesn’t mean form is nonexistent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To me, the priority goes like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Utility&lt;/strong&gt;. Does your software help the consumer perform a unique task in a distinctive way? If it doesn’t, the heart of your software is missing and it will eventually die. Who wants a tool that doesn’t help you accomplish something?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Usability&lt;/strong&gt;. Do you get out of their way so they can execute that task easily and intuitively? Is it reliable, speedy, organized?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Aesthetics&lt;/strong&gt;. Is it attractive in a way that contributes to utility and usability?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By all means, add beauty. Beauty is wonderful. But utility and usability come first because that’s why people are there in the first place. Build around the purpose, then add aesthetics on top of that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your user will thank you for it.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>jrdnbwmn</name></author><category term="product" /><summary type="html">As a product designer, sometimes I question how important beauty is when it comes to software.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Cryptic Startup Terms</title><link href="https://www.jrdnbwmn.com/post/cryptic-startup-terms/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Cryptic Startup Terms" /><published>2018-01-25T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2018-01-25T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://www.jrdnbwmn.com/post/cryptic-startup-terms</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.jrdnbwmn.com/post/cryptic-startup-terms/">&lt;p&gt;The startup world throws around a lot of jargon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of it is fluff, some of it is important.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rather than pretend like you know what people are talking about, I’ve found it’s good to make sure I actually understand the terminology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, here’s a few essential startup terms you should know.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;kpi&quot;&gt;KPI&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stands for Key Performance Indicator. This is a measurable value that indicates how effectively your company or product is achieving its business goals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Example: I would guess a main KPI of AirBnB is &lt;strong&gt;guests per night&lt;/strong&gt; (how many people are staying on an AirBnB property on any given night).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The idea is that you can focus on improving key indicators, which should then directly influence your company’s goals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;churn-rate&quot;&gt;Churn Rate&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your churn rate is the percentage of customers who stop subscribing to your service in a given time period. You can calculate the churn of anything (like revenue or employees), but it’s most often referring to customers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is considered the main enemy of any subscription company.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Example: As of this writing, Buffer’s monthly user churn is &lt;a href=&quot;https://buffer.baremetrics.com/stats/user-churn&quot;&gt;5.9%&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your acceptable churn rate depends entirely on your specific industry and company.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;okr&quot;&gt;OKR&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stands for Objectives &amp;amp; Key Results. This is a framework for setting, communicating, and monitoring goals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Objectives are goals, which tell you where to go. Each objective has key results, which indicate how you’ll get there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Example:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Objective&lt;/strong&gt;: Increase our recurring revenue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Key Results&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;Share of monthly subscriptions increased to 85%.
Average subscription size of at least $295 per month.
Reduce churn to less than 1% per month.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://okrexamples.co/&quot;&gt;More examples&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;mrr&quot;&gt;MRR&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stands for Monthly Recurring Revenue. This is income that a company an reliably anticipate every 30 days. MRR is intended for products or services that have a defined price and recurring term.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Example: As of this writing, Treehouse’s MRR is &lt;a href=&quot;https://getlatka.com/companies/treehouse&quot;&gt;$2M+&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To put two terms together, your MRR churn is the erosion of your monthly recurring revenue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is also ARR: Annual Recurring Revenue, not to be confused with Annual Run Rate (below) which even uses MRR in its calculation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;usp&quot;&gt;USP&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stands for Unique Selling Proposition. This refers to the unique factor of your company or product that sets you apart from all your competition. It’s the answer to the question, “Why should I do business with you instead of anyone else?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Example: M&amp;amp;M’s “Melts in your mouth, not in your hand.” M&amp;amp;Ms use a patented hard sugar coating that keep chocolate from melting in your hands.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;arr&quot;&gt;ARR&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stands for Annual Run Rate. This is a method used to project future revenue based on your current revenue. To get it, simply multiply your MRR by 12.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While that might seem inaccurate, ARR is a helpful tool to get an idea of long term growth and visualize the size of your business.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Example: If a company’s MRR for last month was $100k, its current ARR $1.2M.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;burn-rate&quot;&gt;Burn rate&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your burn rate is the rate at which your company spends money in excess of income. It’s a measure of negative cash flow. It is usually quoted in terms of cash spent (lost) per month.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Burn rate a good measuring stick for a company’s runway — the amount of time it has before it runs out of money.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Example: If a company has $1 million in the bank, makes $100k per month, and spends $200k per month, it has a burn rate of $100,000/month. It also has a runway of 10 months.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>jrdnbwmn</name></author><category term="terminology" /><summary type="html">The startup world throws around a lot of jargon.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Legacy of AIM</title><link href="https://www.jrdnbwmn.com/post/the-legacy-of-aim/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Legacy of AIM" /><published>2017-12-15T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2017-12-15T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://www.jrdnbwmn.com/post/the-legacy-of-aim</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.jrdnbwmn.com/post/the-legacy-of-aim/">&lt;p&gt;On a cold February morning in 1997, America Online filed a patent for something that was to become the basis of hundreds of social tech startups.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They called it the “Buddy List.” It was the heart of the digital social structure that formed AOL Instant Messenger.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first words of the &lt;a href=&quot;http://patft.uspto.gov/netacgi/nph-Parser?Query=PN%2F6750881&amp;amp;RefSrch=yes&amp;amp;Sect2=HITOFF&amp;amp;Sect2=PTO1&amp;amp;d=PALL&amp;amp;f=G&amp;amp;l=50&amp;amp;p=1&amp;amp;r=1&amp;amp;u=%2Fnetahtml%2FPTO%2Fsearch-bool.html&quot;&gt;patent&lt;/a&gt; abstract explained:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The invention implements a real time notification system that tracks, for each user, the logon status of selected co-users of an on-line or network system and displays that information in real time to the tracking user in a unique graphical interface.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you were a 90’s kid, chances are you remember what a Buddy List was. You likely recall the AIM install CD, your screen name, and how much effort went into your carefully crafted away messages. You can probably reminisce about competing for time on the home computer so you could chat with your friends.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The world had never seen anything like it. And it captivated us all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, AOL Instant Messenger is shutting down for good, 20 years after it launched.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But what it established lives on. AOL didn’t know it back then, and we don’t realize it today, but AIM is the father of our modern social web.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don’t believe me? Let’s start with the Buddy List.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;buddy-list&quot;&gt;Buddy List&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Think about what’s at the foundation of any social media you use today. It’s that list of other human beings. Followers, friends, whatever they’re called. Social media doesn’t work without these groups of real people and it all originated with the Buddy List.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Buddy List was exactly what you’d think — your list of friends. You controlled who was on it. You could find new people through information they put in their profile, but you had to both agree to the connection — if you were on their buddy list, they were on yours.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most important feature of the buddy list was the ability to see whether each person was online. This remarkable little feature created a way to “feel” that your friends were around. There was an intimacy and immediacy to it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Being on someone’s buddy list meant something. Nothing had ever come along like this before AIM, where you had a digital group of connections tied to your real relationships.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;away-messages&quot;&gt;Away Messages&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If one of your friends wasn’t online, you’d see their “away message.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Have you ever written a tweet or status update? Then you’ve gone through the same process AIM users went through to write away messages. It is the ancestor of those widely-used features.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The away message started as a set of three default options: online, busy, or away. But then AOL set up the ability to write a custom message and it quickly transformed into a way to express yourself to your buddies. From simple plans you had for the day, to quoting lyrics from your favorite songs, the away message let you broadcast anything to the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;profiles&quot;&gt;Profiles&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The modern digital profile is quite a remarkable thing. In essence, it represents the notion that we can have a web persona that we completely control.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve all agonized over the perfect profile pic or handle. We make conscious decisions about cover images and bios so that we present to the world exactly the image that we want.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That all started on AIM.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The service let you choose things like an avatar, bio, fonts, and colors, but your biggest decision was your screen name. It could be anything from xXPunkRockPonyXx to InternetDiane. The possibilities of every alphanumeric combination allowed you to choose something meaningful, personal, and easily recognizable, so that’s what everyone did.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This kind of customization helped us realize how what an online persona could be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;messaging&quot;&gt;Messaging&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Online instant messaging hit a sweet spot. It was better than email and less formal than a phone call. It fit right in with what the rising generation wanted as a form of communication.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s still something we can’t get enough of 20 years later. The underlying concepts of Facebook Messenger, WhatsApp, Slack, Discord, and Snapchat all began with AIM.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is where communication and real human connection actually happened. Things like late night chats with your best friend about the latest music or deliberately worded conversations with that girl or boy you had a crush on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was all about the contact with other human beings over the internet in a real, direct, private, and personal way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-running-man&quot;&gt;The Running Man&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;AIM could be considered the first social media superpower. It was a digital consumer tool used at an unprecedented scale, a household name.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It defined the social potential of the web for Americans. Perhaps more than any other product, AIM helped establish the internet as a place to hang out rather than a simple utility.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Entrepreneurs realized that, too. AIM was the starting point of an exponential trend in social web startups. Companies like Twitter, YouTube, Facebook, LinkedIn, Pinterest, and Instagram are some of the major players who have ridden that wave.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The running yellow figure of AIM’s logo seems fitting in retrospect. The idea of always on, always transmitting captured the feeling quite well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now the runner is passing the baton.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;~~ ADBB ~~&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>jrdnbwmn</name></author><category term="product" /><summary type="html">On a cold February morning in 1997, America Online filed a patent for something that was to become the basis of hundreds of social tech startups.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Building Yelp</title><link href="https://www.jrdnbwmn.com/post/building-yelp/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Building Yelp" /><published>2017-12-05T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2017-12-05T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://www.jrdnbwmn.com/post/building-yelp</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.jrdnbwmn.com/post/building-yelp/">&lt;p&gt;In the fall of 2004, Jeremy Stoppelman caught the flu.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He had just arrived in San Francisco that summer, so he jumped online in hopes of finding a recommendation for a doctor. Instead, all Stoppelman found were bare bones directories and useless information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But this gave him an idea. He and Russel Simmons were in San Francisco working for a business incubator called MRL Ventures, searching for “the next big thing” on the internet. He met with Simmons over lunch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/1200/1*cF41tRIYL_5tag6XjGFBRw.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Early photo of the founders&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The two were in the office of their boss, Max Levchin, pitching their new concept before dinnertime. They didn’t have a PowerPoint presentation or a specific revenue plan; just a sense that they could make something that would appeal to lots of people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Levchin hesitated. “I wasn’t sure if it would work. But the guys were really enthusiastic about it. And in my experience, when you have smart people who work well together, it’s foolish not to invest.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maybe he was feeling lucky because it was his 29th birthday, or maybe it was those tens of millions laying around from his recent &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wikiwand.com/en/Max_Levchin#/PayPal&quot;&gt;exit from PayPal&lt;/a&gt;, but Levchin agreed. He invested $1 million in the half-baked idea and Stoppelman and Simmons got to work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;yelp-10&quot;&gt;Yelp 1.0&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what were they building? The two founders realized from Stoppelman’s doctor experience that the best way to find a business was through word of mouth. But word of mouth hadn’t moved to the web yet. The question they were asking was, “How do we bring those in-person recommendations online?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They thought the answer was email and that’s exactly what the earliest version of Yelp was. On the website Simmons put together, users could email their friends asking for recommendations on specific locations or types of places. Responses were logged on a communal site for everyone to see.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their first review came in on October 12, 2004. Katherine W. gave Truly Mediterranean four stars and a simple, but convincing:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“dirt cheap, good falafels.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite that promising review, their idea was a flop. It attracted few users beyond the founders’ friends and family and failed to impress the venture capital investors whom Stoppelman pitched at the end of 2004.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We got the doors slammed in our face over and over again,” Stoppelman said. Things were starting to fizzle right before their eyes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-epiphany&quot;&gt;The Epiphany&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Undeterred, the founders searched for a way to improve their product. One day, they noticed something.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The site had a link, buried somewhere in the footer, that you could click if you wanted to submit a review without being asked. While poring over their analytics, they realized that people were not only finding that link, they were beginning to use it — often.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They watched as users submitted unsolicited reviews more and more. It got even bigger than the email-requested reviews. People would write 5, 10, or 15 reviews in one sitting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They knew they had stumbled upon something big. So in February 2005, the duo launched a brand new site, this time focused entirely on unsolicited reviews. Yelp 2.0 saw an immediate rise in traffic. It was a hit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-foundation&quot;&gt;The Foundation&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To kick-start the process of building a platform for this new review system, they purchased a database of over 20 million business locations. This database was old and inaccurate, but it created the framework for what Yelp called “claimed business locations”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The empty business pages functioned as an open invitation for people to submit reviews. It motivated people to, at the very least, write a few words about the business. In fact, many of the early reviews were just that: “this place is great”, or “this place sucked.” But as time passed, reviewers started to take the platform more seriously and write longer, deeper reviews. The framework paid off in dividends later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, they didn’t subordinate the user’s contributions to professional reviews, as on Citysearch, or to directory information, like yellow-pages sites. Instead, Yelp motivated people to share reviews through praise and attention , something no one else was doing. Those social networking features were what made them stand out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;getting-social&quot;&gt;Getting Social&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that they had the right direction, they needed to grow their user base. Without the cash for a national rollout, Stoppelman decided to first focus on making Yelp famous locally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the help of a buzz-marketing guru he hired on a whim, Stoppelman decided to select a few dozen people — the most active reviewers on the site — and throw them an open-bar party. As a joke, he called the group the Yelp Elite Squad.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/2000/1*tw43stnSQV1ogeMWQxjmsw.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;A Yelp Elite Event&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Levchin thought the idea was crazy: “I was like, ‘Holy crap, we’re nowhere near profitability; this is ridiculous,’ “. But 100 people showed up to the first party, and traffic to the site began to increase. Since the parties were reserved for prolific reviewers, they gave casual users a reason to use the site more and nonusers a reason to join.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By June 2005, Yelp had 12,000 reviewers, most of them in the Bay Area. In November, Stoppelman went back to the VCs and bagged $5 million from Bessemer Venture Partners. He used the money to throw more parties and hire party planners — Yelp called them “community managers” — in New York, Chicago, and Boston. Community managers and the Yelp Elite Squad still exist today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;stickers&quot;&gt;Stickers&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The number of reviewers on the site grew to 100,000 by 2006. Stoppelman also raised several million more in venture capital. By summer 2006, Yelp had one million monthly visitors and they were slowly adding more cities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that user counts were growing, they focused on their next problem: they needed to get merchants to play a much deeper role. A growing user base of reviewers was wonderful, but the other side of the coin was the businesses themselves. Not to mention they were Yelp’s only source of revenue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They decided to begin an aggressive drive to get merchants to claim business listings, populate them (e.g. menus, hours, website, etc), and motivate their own customers to review their experiences on Yelp.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/1200/1*stZmCHgt2FOrspxGZIMLVg.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;The Yelp Sticker&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the ways they did this was by using a sticker. It was a genius move.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most businesses were already familiar with Zagat and Mobile stickers and the impact they had on awareness. But Yelp was more aggressive with it and even handed out extra marketing materials. This had a remarkable effect on the review count. Organic review counts shot up and more businesses got on board.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yelp stickers became almost ubiquitous at famous restaurants in the Bay Area and continue to serve the company today. They stand as a daily reminder of Yelp to the potential reviewer, the potential visitor, and the merchant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;yelps-legacy&quot;&gt;Yelp’s Legacy&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stoppelman, Simmons, and the rest of the Yelp team were persistent, humble enough to pivot, and savvy enough to see the real problems they faced and to use creative methods to overcome them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yelp continued to grow. The service kept adding cities and eventually went international. They launched a successful mobile app. Stoppelman gathered tens of millions in venture capital and then took it IPO. As of this writing, the company has a market cap of almost &lt;a href=&quot;quotes.wsj.com/YELP&quot;&gt;$3.7 billion&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They’ve made a few mistakes along the way, and some say they’re in the middle of a process of &lt;a href=&quot;https://hbr.org/2015/12/what-is-disruptive-innovation&quot;&gt;disruption&lt;/a&gt;. But Yelp — the original king of place reviews — spawned a score of apps and startups and changed the way consumers view their relationship with businesses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For that, they get…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/1600/1*ef8MiAD7j4_6cI4fHfCfFQ.png&quot; alt=&quot;Five Stars&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>jrdnbwmn</name></author><category term="growth" /><summary type="html">In the fall of 2004, Jeremy Stoppelman caught the flu.</summary></entry></feed>